An Efficient Quantum Classifier Based on Hamiltonian Representations
Federico Tiblias1,3, Anna Schroeder2,3,5,
Yue Zhang4, Mariami Gachechiladze2,3, and Iryna Gurevych1,3
1 Ubiquitous Knowledge Processing Lab (UKP Lab), Hessian Center for AI (hessian.AI)
2 Quantum Computing Group
3 Department of Computer Science, Technical University of Darmstadt
4 School of Engineering, Westlake University
5 Merck KGaA, Darmstadt, Germany
Abstract
Quantum machine learning (QML) is a disci-
pline that seeks to transfer the advantages of
quantum computing to data-driven tasks. How-
ever, many studies rely on toy datasets or heavy
feature reduction, raising concerns about their
scalability. Progress is further hindered by hard-
ware limitations and the significant costs of
encoding dense vector representations on quan-
tum devices. To address these challenges, we
propose an efficient approach called Hamilto-
nian classifier that circumvents the costs asso-
ciated with data encoding by mapping inputs
to a finite set of Pauli strings and computing
predictions as their expectation values. In addi-
tion, we introduce two classifier variants with
different scaling in terms of parameters and
sample complexity. We evaluate our approach
on text and image classification tasks, against
well-established classical and quantum mod-
els. The Hamiltonian classifier delivers per-
formance comparable to or better than these
methods. Notably, our method achieves log-
arithmic complexity in both qubits and quan-
tum gates, making it well-suited for large-scale,
real-world applications. We make our imple-
mentation available on GitHub1.
1 Introduction
In recent years, interest in quantum computing has
grown significantly due to the provable advantages
in computational complexity and memory usage
some algorithms exhibit over their best classical
analogues (Nielsen and Chuang, 2000; Quetschlich
et al., 2024; Biamonte et al., 2017). For instance,
efficient algorithms exist that can solve problems
such as integer factorization (Shor, 1997), Fourier
transform (Camps et al., 2021), and specific in-
stances of matrix inversion (Harrow et al., 2009)
with an exponential speedup over the fastest known
classical methods. Other notable results include
1https://github.com/UKPLab/arxiv2025-ham-classifier
Input
encoding
Parametrized
transformations Measurement
Awesome
movie!
Awesome
movie!
Awesome
movie!
Figure 1: (Top) Schema of a flipped model: data is
represented as a measurement avoiding input encod-
ing. (Bottom) The proposed input-to-measurement map-
ping: data is vectorized, mapped to a Hamiltonian via
outer product, decomposed into a small number of Pauli
strings, and recomposed into a simplified Hamiltonian
Grover’s algorithm, which performs an unstruc-
tured search achieving a O(√n) time complexity,
a quadratic improvement over the fastest classical
approach that scales as O(n) (Grover, 1996). In
parallel with these theoretical developments, the
size of publicly accessible quantum machines has
been steadily growing, and several companies have
begun offering commercial cloud access to these
devices (Yang et al., 2023).
Quantum machine learning is an offshoot of
quantum computing that seeks to extend its ad-
vantages to data-driven methods. The leading
paradigm revolves around variational quantum cir-
cuits (VQCs), quantum algorithms whose parame-
ters can be adjusted with classical optimization to
solve a specific problem (Cerezo et al., 2021). This
approach is sometimes referred to as quantum neu-
ral networks given the similarities with the classical
counterpart (Farhi and Neven, 2018; Killoran et al.,
2019). Prior works have found some evidence that
1
arXiv:2504.10542v1  [quant-ph]  13 Apr 2025
QML algorithms can offer improvements over their
classical analogues in terms of capacity (Abbas
et al., 2021), expressive power (Du et al., 2020),
and generalization (Caro et al., 2022).
Despite the advancements of VQCs, a large-
scale demonstration of advantage - the ability of
a quantum computer to solve a problem faster,
with fewer resources or better performance than
any classical counterpart - remains out of reach
for QML algorithms. Current quantum machines,
referred to as Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum
(NISQ) devices (Preskill, 2018), are restricted both
in size and complexity of the operations they can
perform (Zaman et al., 2023). Qubits, the basic
units of quantum computation, are hard to main-
tain in a state useful for computation, and scaling
quantum processors to a size suitable for QML
remains a significant challenge. Moreover, the
widespread use of dense and unstructured vector
representations in modern machine learning archi-
tectures (Bengio et al., 2000) makes their transla-
tion into quantum equivalents challenging. Specif-
ically, the processes of loading data onto a quan-
tum device, known as encoding, and extracting re-
sults from it, referred to as measurement, can scale
rapidly in terms of qubit requirements or compu-
tational costs (Schuld and Killoran, 2022). These
costs may grow prohibitively with input size, po-
tentially negating any quantum advantage. As a
result, researchers are often forced to down-scale
their experiments making it unclear whether these
findings generalize at larger scales (Bowles et al.,
2024; Mingard et al., 2024).
Motivated by these limitations, we propose a
scheme to efficiently encode and measure classi-
cal data from quantum devices and demonstrate its
effectiveness across different tasks. The method
we propose is a specific instance of a flipped
model (Jerbi et al., 2024), a type of circuit which
encodes data as the observable of a quantum circuit
rather than as a quantum state, effectively bypass-
ing the need for input encoding (Figure 1). From
a linear algebra perspective, this corresponds to
learning a vector representation of the classifica-
tion problem and using the input data to compute
projections of this vector. The magnitude of these
projected vectors is then used to make predictions.
In quantum-mechanical terms, unstructured input
data is mapped onto Pauli strings which are then
combined to construct a Hamiltonian. The classi-
fier prediction is obtained as the expectation value
of this Hamiltonian. We improve over the standard
flipped model by providing a mapping from inputs
to observables that achieves a favourable logarith-
mic qubit and gate complexity relative to the input
dimensionality (Figure 1). We also introduce two
variants that trade some classification performance
in exchange for smaller model size and better sam-
ple complexity, respectively. Crucially, the scaling
exhibited by these models allows them to be exe-
cuted on quantum devices and simulated on classi-
cal hardware at scales already meaningful for NLP
tasks. In brief, this paper provides the following
contributions:
C1 A novel encoding scheme achieving logarith-
mic qubit and gate complexity;
C2 Variants of this scheme with different
performance-cost tradeoffs;
C3 A thorough evaluation of our scheme on text
and image classification tasks, against estab-
lished quantum and classical baselines.
2 Background
Quantum computers differ fundamentally from
classical computers, utilizing the principles of
quantum physics rather than binary logic imple-
mented by transistors. For readers unfamiliar with
the topic, in Appendix A we offer a brief introduc-
tion to the notation and formalize the concepts of
qubit, gate, measurement, and Pauli decomposition.
In this section, we instead discuss how these de-
vices have been used to tackle machine learning
problems, as well as their limitations.
2.1 Data encoding
The first step for quantum-based ML algorithms
is state preparation, the process of representing
input data as quantum states. Most algorithms
share similarities in how they achieve this (Rath
and Date, 2023). The choice of encoding severely
impacts the runtime of the circuit as well as its
expressivity (Sim et al., 2019). Basis encoding
is the simplest representation analogous to classi-
cal bits. An n-element bit string

x1 x2 . . . xn

is represented in the basis states of n qubits asNn
i=1 |xi⟩ = |x1 . . . xn⟩ (e.g. 011 is represented
as |011⟩). This representation requires O(n) qubits.
Angle encoding represents continuous data as the
phase of qubits. A set of n continuous variables
x1 x2 . . . xn

can be represented over n qubits
as Nn
j=1 Rˆσ(xj) |0⟩ with Rˆσ(x) = e−ixˆσ a so-
called rotation gate, and ˆσ a Pauli matrix X, Y
2
or Z that specifies the rotation axis. Amplitude
encoding represents a vector of N = 2n values
x1 x2 . . . xN

over n qubits as PN−1
i=0 xi |i⟩,
where {|i⟩}N
i=1 corresponds to the canonical or-
thonormal basis written in a binary representation.
There is a trade-off between ease of encoding
and qubit count: basis and angle encoding useO(n)
gates for O(n) values over O(n) qubits, while am-
plitude encoding handles N-dimensional inputs
but needs O(N) gates over O(n) qubits, an expo-
nential increase in input size but also gates. An-
gle encoding strategies often embed multiple fea-
tures onto the same qubit to reduce qubit usage,
effectively a form of pooling (Pérez-Salinas et al.,
2020; Du et al., 2020). Amplitude encoding, on
the other hand, is often performed using easy-to-
prepare quantum states to mitigate its gate complex-
ity (Ashhab, 2022; Du et al., 2020). In text-related
tasks, encoding schemes typically encode words
over a set number of qubits (Wu et al., 2021; Lorenz
et al., 2021), while in image tasks, pixel values are
directly encoded as angles or amplitudes (Cong
et al., 2019; Wei et al., 2022).
2.2 Variational quantum circuits
Once data has been encoded in a quantum com-
puter, it is processed by a quantum circuit to obtain
a prediction. One of the leading paradigms for
QML revolves around VQCs (also called quantum
ansätze, or parametrized quantum circuits), a type
of circuit where the action of gates is controlled
by classical parameters. The training loop of a
VQC closely resembles that of classical neural net-
works (Cerezo et al., 2021): input data is encoded
in the quantum device as a quantum state, several
layers of parametrized gates transform this state, a
prediction is obtained via quantum measurement,
and finally, a specialized but classical optimizer
(Wierichs et al., 2022) computes a loss and updates
the parameters. VQCs have shown better conver-
gence during training (Abbas et al., 2021) as well as
better expressive power (Du et al., 2020) compared
to neural networks of similar size.
Several VQC-based equivalents of classical ar-
chitectures have been proposed such as auto-
encoders (Romero et al., 2017), GNNs (Dallaire-
Demers and Killoran, 2018), and CNNs (Cong
et al., 2019; Henderson et al., 2020). Quantum NLP
works have focused on implementing VQCs with
favourable inductive biases for text, such as quan-
tum RNNs (Bausch, 2020; Li et al., 2023), quantum
LSTMs (Chen et al., 2022), and quantum attention
layers (Cherrat et al., 2022; Shi et al., 2023; Zhao
et al., 2024), with recent works showcasing appli-
cability of these methods at scales meaningful for
NLP applications (Xu et al., 2024)
2.3 Quantum Machine Learning limitations
Despite these achievements, QML applications
have yet to demonstrate a practical quantum ad-
vantage. Firstly, NISQ devices are limited in terms
of the number of qubits in a single device, con-
nectivity between the qubits, noise in the compu-
tation, and coherence time (Zaman et al., 2023;
Anschuetz and Kiani, 2022). Secondly, quantum
devices have fundamental difficulties in dealing
with the dense and unstructured vector represen-
tations around which ML revolves: loading (or
encoding) data into a quantum state either requires
a large number of qubits (for angle and basis encod-
ing) or a prohibitive amount of gates (for amplitude
encoding). Efficient methods for amplitude encod-
ing (Ashhab, 2022; Wang et al., 2009) incur trade-
offs in the expressivity of vectors that have not
been explored sufficiently in the context of QML.
Moreover, measurement is an expensive process
extracting only one bit of information per qubit
measured. Extracting a real-valued vector from
a quantum computer generally requires exponen-
tially many measurements (Schuld and Petruccione,
2021). As a result, many current QML experiments
are limited in both scale and scope in order to fit
within the constraints of NISQ devices and simula-
tors. Small datasets, typically consisting of only a
few hundred samples, are often used (Senokosov
et al., 2024; Li et al., 2023; Liu et al., 2021; Chen,
2022). Additionally, aggressive dimensionality re-
duction is commonly performed to reduce data to
just a few dozen features (Bausch, 2020; Zhao et al.,
2024). In contrast, even "small" classical neural
networks by modern standards are several orders
of magnitude larger in terms of parameters, dataset
size, and representation dimensionality (Mingard
et al., 2024). These limitations have raised con-
cerns about the applicability of QML results to
larger, more complex tasks. Some question whether
the observed performance is due to the quantum
model itself or the upstream pre-processing (Chen
et al., 2021), while others highlight the difficulty
of generalizing these results to larger datasets and
the challenges of fair benchmarking (Bowles et al.,
2024; Mingard et al., 2024). Several other chal-
lenges remain, including barren plateaus (Larocca
et al., 2024), development of efficient optimization
3
algorithms for VQCs (Wiedmann et al., 2023), and
error correction (Chatterjee et al., 2023).
To mitigate the data loading and read-out chal-
lenges, the flipped model has been recently intro-
duced (Jerbi et al., 2024), where quantum resources
are only required during training, while inference
can happen classically. Although flipped models on
NISQ devices are classically simulatable and thus
cannot yet achieve quantum advantage, they hold
significant promise when combined with shadow
techniques (Huang et al., 2020; Song et al., 2023),
which allow the prediction of many quantum sys-
tem properties from a limited number of measure-
ments. There are theoretically provable instances
where shadow-flipped models outperform classi-
cal methods under widely-believed cryptography
assumptions (Gyurik and Dunjko, 2022). The guar-
antees of flipped models, as well as their scalability,
warrant their exploration in the context of NLP.
3 Hamiltonian classifier
In the following, we describe a flipped model that
improves over previous works by sensibly lowering
qubit requirements. To the best of our knowledge,
we are the first to apply flipped models to text clas-
sification and to provide a thorough evaluation of
such methods across multiple datasets, compar-
ing against classical and quantum baselines. We
also propose two variants that further reduce model
size and sample complexity with minimal impact
on performance and extend flipped models to the
multi-class scenario.
3.1 Fully-parametrized Hamiltonian (HAM)
Our Hamiltonian classifier takes as in-
put a sequence of embeddings x =
x1 x2 . . . xs

, xi ∈ Rd and outputs a
prediction probability fθ,ϕ, a real number repre-
senting the estimated class the input belongs to.
Similarly to VQCs, gradient descent is used to
optimize the classifier parameters θ, ϕon a given
training set X with binary labels y. The classifier
can encode embeddings of size at most N = 2n
with the remaining N − d dimensions padded to 0.
The optimization problem can be summarized as:
arg min
θ,ϕ
1
|X|
X
x∈X,y∈y
L(fθ,ϕ(x), y), (1)
fθ,ϕ(x) := σ(ψ†
θHϕ(x)ψθ) (2)
Hϕ(x) := H0
ϕ + 1
s
sX
i=1
xix⊤
i (3)
ψθ := Uθ |0⟩⊗n = Uθ

1 0 ··· 0
⊤ . (4)
Hϕ ∈ RN×N is the Hamiltonian of our system,
and is constructed from embeddings x and a bias
term H0
ϕ ∈ RN×N (Eq. 3). The bias term is a fully
parametrized Hermitian matrix, giving more fine-
grained control over the Hamiltonian. Uθ ∈ CN×N
represents a VQC, and ψθ is the result of applying
said VQC to the starting state (Eq. 4). The spe-
cific choice of VQC is application-dependant and
we experiment with three qubit-efficient circuits
during hyperparameter tuning, which we discuss
in Appendix B. The prediction probability fθ,ϕ is
regularized using the sigmoid function σ (Eq. 2).
Finally, parameters θ, ϕare optimized classically
to minimize the loss function L, the cross entropy.
When building Uθ and ψθ, they are not explicitly
represented as dense matrices in classical form. In-
stead, they are constructed directly on quantum
hardware from a manageable set of parameters,
avoiding the need for large-scale classical represen-
tations. By encoding inputs of size d ≤ N over n
qubits, we attain logarithmic scaling in the number
of qubits and an overall sample complexity that
scales quadratically in the embedding size. We
expand on this in Section 3.4.
3.2 Parameter-efficient Hamiltonian (PEFF)
The bias term H0
ϕ of HAM significantly contributes
to its parameter count, resulting in a O(N2) scal-
ing. To lower the model size, we experiment with
applying a bias term bϕ ∈ Rd directly to the input
embeddings as ˜xi := xi + bϕ. This term skews
the distribution in the vector space while only re-
quiring O(d) parameters. The Hamiltonian is then
constructed as Hϕ(˜x) := 1
s
Ps
i=1 ˜xi˜x.
Physically implementing the Hamiltonians of
HAM and PEFF requires first decomposing them
into observables the quantum device can measure
and then performing measurements for each ob-
servable separately. As we detail in Appendix A,
this process is potentially expensive, requiring an
exponential number of operations. In the follow-
4
Adding bias term
Mapping to 
Pauli strings
State preparation
Expectation value 
computation
Figure 2: The SIM model at a glance. In green, parts
that are stored classically, in blue, parts that can be
represented on quantum computers.
ing, we show how the model can be restructured to
drastically reduce this cost.
3.3 Simplified Hamiltonian (SIM) variant
To address the computational challenges we de-
scribe above, we propose an extension of PEFF
that constructs the Hamiltonian from a small num-
ber p of Pauli strings, circumventing the need for
an expensive decomposition and reducing the num-
ber of necessary measurements to O(p) (Figure
2). More information about Pauli strings can be
found in Appendix A. We define p Pauli strings
P1, P2, . . . Pp ∈ Pn (in practice, they can be cho-
sen at random) and use them to compute the corre-
sponding coefficients α1, α2, . . . αp from H:
˜x := 1
s
sX
i=1
xi + bϕ (5)
Hϕ(˜x) := ˜x˜x⊤ (6)
αi = 1
2n Tr(PiHϕ) = 1
2n ˜x⊤Pi˜x (7)
˜Hϕ(˜x) :=
pX
j=1
αjwjPj, (8)
where wj ∈ R is a learned parameter that re-
weights the effect of Pauli strings. Pj and Hϕ
in Eq. 7 are generally large matrices, but several
algorithms exist that side-step the costs of full mul-
tiplication by exploiting the structure of the Pauli
string (Koska et al., 2024; Hantzko et al., 2024).
For this method, we choose to redefine Hϕ (Eq. 5
and 6) in a way that allows replacing the expen-
sive matrix-matrix product PiHϕ with two more
efficient vector-matrix products ˜x⊤Pi˜x, thus im-
proving scaling.
To emphasize the underlying transformation, we
recast the expectation value computation in SIM:
fθ,ϕ(˜x) =σ
 1
2n
pX
j=1
˜x†Pj ˜xwjψ†
θPjψθ

. (9)
Equation 9 shows that SIM computes a weighted
sum of several feature maps ˜x†Pj ˜x, where the
weights are determined by both the learned termwj
and the factor ψ†
θPjψθ. These two terms concur to
select the feature maps most relevant for solving the
problem. During our exploration, we observe that
removing wj significantly degrades performance.
We speculate this occurs because ψ†
θPjψθ is con-
strained to the range [−1, 1], whereas the presence
of wj introduces a notion of magnitude that facil-
itates training. A related approach is discussed
in Huang and Rebentrost (2024), which focuses
on improving variational strategies rather than di-
rectly addressing the challenges of input encod-
ing. We believe that these two methods could be
synergistically combined to further reduce overall
computational costs.
All proposed methods output a prediction prob-
ability fθ,ϕ to be interpreted as a binary label. We
can extend this to a scenario with c distinct classes
by using a one-vs-many approach: either Uθ, bϕ
or w can be tied to a specific class to obtain a
class-specific discriminator. We choose a setup that
learns c distinct re-weightings w1, w2, . . . wc and
build c separate Hamiltonians ˜H1
ϕ, ˜H2
ϕ, . . .˜Hc
ϕ so
that each one discriminates a single class. For class
k, we have Hk
ϕ(˜x) := Pp
j=1 αjwk
j Pj. Parameter
count scales as O(c), although different choices
of parameter sharing strongly affect the final num-
ber. Since our setup learns different weights for
the same Pauli strings across classes, expectation
values on a real quantum device can be computed
only once and then post-processed to obtain proba-
bilities for all classes.
3.4 Complexity analysis
In this section, we compare the theoretical qubit
count, gate complexity, and sample complexity of
our classifier with other established models from
the literature. We consider a subset of implementa-
tions from the literature that we consider represen-
tative of the current discourse. Our three variants
all achieve a qubit count that scales as the logarithm
of the input dimensionality. This is determined by
5
the number of qubits required to encode a large
enough Hamiltonian. For our models, gate com-
plexity depends entirely on the chosen circuit Uθ.
The ansätze we consider throughout our experi-
ments result in a linear or quadratic scaling. Sam-
ple complexity, defined as the total number of Pauli
strings to measure in order to obtain a prediction,
both HAM and PEFF necessitate a full evaluation
of the Hamiltonian, resulting in a complexity of
O(4n). Since 4log2(d) = 2log2(d2), we conclude
that the sample complexity isO(d2). Notably, SIM
combines the logarithmic scaling in qubit and gate
complexity of the other variants with a constant
sample complexity made possible by simplifying
the Hamiltonian, making it a strong candidate for
practical implementation on NISQ devices. The
full comparison is shown in Table 1. For readability,
we omit the precision term arising when running
these methods on quantum hardware. All models
incur an additional 1/ϵ2 term in sample complexity,
where ϵ is the desired precision.
4 Experiments
4.1 Datasets & Pre-processing
To evaluate the capabilities of our models, we se-
lect a diverse set of tasks encompassing both text
and image data, covering binary and multi-class
scenarios. To facilitate replicability, our scripts au-
tomatically download all datasets on the first run.
Text datasets We first consider the GLUE Stan-
ford Sentiment Treebank (SST) dataset as obtained
from HuggingFace2 (Socher et al., 2013; Wang
et al., 2019). It consists of ∼ 70k single sen-
tences extracted from movie reviews whose senti-
ment (positive/negative) was annotated by 3 human
judges. We then evaluate our method on the IMDb
Large Movie Review Dataset (Maas et al., 2011)
containing 50k highly polar movie reviews. We
also consider the AG News (Zhang et al., 2015)
classification task as a benchmark for our multi-
class model. AG News consists of ∼ 128k news
articles divided by topic (world, sports, business,
sci/tech). These are commonplace datasets rea-
sonably close to real-world applications. For text
datasets, we remove all punctuation, lowercase all
text, tokenize with a whitespace strategy, and fi-
nally embed tokens with word2vec 3 to obtain a
sequence x. The resulting embedding has size
2https://huggingface.co/datasets/stanfordnlp/sst2
3https://code.google.com/archive/p/word2vec/
d = 300 and requires n = 9 qubits to be repre-
sented in our methods.
Image datasets As a sanity check, we con-
sider a binary version of MNIST which only in-
cludes digits 0 and 1. We then consider Fashion-
MNIST (Xiao et al., 2017), a dataset of 60k
grayscale images of clothes subdivided into 10
classes. Feeding images directly to our models
results in d = 784 and n = 10. We further ex-
periment on a binarized version of the CIFAR-10
dataset (Krizhevsky, 2012) we name CIFAR-2 ob-
tained by grouping the original ten classes into two
categories: vehicles and animals. The 32×32 RGB
images result in d = 1024 features over n = 10
qubits. We also note that no further pre-processing
or dimensionality reduction is performed to pre-
serve the original properties of the images. MNIST
and Fashion-MNIST representations are not se-
quential and therefore are considered by our model
as a special case with s = 1, while in CIFAR-2
each channel is considered as a different element
of a sequence with s = 3.
4.2 Baselines
We compare our classifiers (HAM, PEFF, SIM)
with three quantum baselines: a QLSTM (Chen
et al., 2022), a QCNN (Cong et al., 2019), and a
simple circuit ansatz (CIRC). QLSTM and QCNN
have been adapted from implementations of the
original papers. CIRC is our implementation and
consists of an amplitude encoding for the input, the
same hardware-efficient ansätze of HAM, and a
linear regression on the circuit’s output state. Note
that running CIRC in practice would require state
tomography, this setup is therefore not meant to
be efficient or scalable but rather to give a best-
case scenario of a VQC of similar complexity to
our classifier. We also compare with out-of-the-box
classical baselines: a multi-layer perception (MLP),
a logistic regression (LOG), an RNN, an LSTM,
and a CNN. MLP and LOG act on the mean-pooled
embedding of the sequence.
4.3 Experimental setting
We first perform a random search on hyperparam-
eters such as learning rate, batch size, number of
qubits, and number of layers to identify the best
configuration of each architecture. For the sake
of brevity, a more detailed discussion is moved to
Appendix B. After identifying the best hyperparam-
eters, we train 10 models for each architecture with
randomized seeds on the original training split and
6
Model Reference Qubit count Gate complexity Sample complexity
QCNN Henderson et al. (2020) O(d) O(d2) O(2d)
Cong et al. (2019) O(log d) O(d + l log d) O(p)
QLSTM Chen et al. (2022) O(d) O(ld) O(d)
QNN Farhi and Neven (2018) O(d) O(l) O(1)
Mitarai et al. (2018) O(d) O(ld) O(1)
Schuld et al. (2020) O(log d) O(d + l log d) O(1)
HAM Ours O(log d) O(l log d) or O(l log(d)2) O(d2)
PEFF Ours O(log d) O(l log d) or O(l log(d)2) O(d2)
SIM Ours O(log d) O(l log d) or O(l log(d)2) O(p)
Table 1: Theoretical scaling comparison of various VQCs, with d input size, l number of layers, and p number of
Pauli strings to measure (defined as a hyperparameter).
SST2 IMDb AG News
Model # Params Train Test* # Params Train Test # Params Train Test
LOG 301 84.7 80.4 301 85.8 85.5 1204 90.1 89.2
MLP 180901 97.5 80.2 180901 88.1 85.8 40604 90.2 89.1
LSTM 241701 97.8 84.4 241600 99.3 88.4 242004 91.5 90.5
RNN 40301 89.6 80.1 60501 79.7 78.1 40604 88.8 88.1
CIRC 923 85.2 80.1 923 86.1 85.8 2387 89.7 89.2
QLSTM 2766 89.9 84.4 4679 76.8 67.9 3582 87.2 86.7
HAM 130854 91.2 82.3 130926 91.0 88.1 - - -
PEFF 410 81.8 80.0 410 84.0 83.8 - - -
SIM 1338 80.6 79.0 1410 86.0 85.3 4416 89.4 88.6
Table 2: Accuracies across text datasets. Results are averaged over 10 runs or (*) run achieving lowest training loss.
average their performance on the test split. The
only exception is the SST2 dataset for which no
test set is provided. In this case, we select the run
achieving the lowest training loss and submit it to
GLUE’s website to get a test score. Appendix C
shows additional experiments in which we further
investigate architectural choices such as bias, state
preparation, and number of Pauli strings. With the
exception of QCNN which is implemented in Pen-
nyLane, all quantum operations are simulated in
PyTorch as it allows batching several Hamiltonians
thus enabling efficient training. We do not simu-
late noise in order to assess the performance of our
approach under an ideal scenario. For all tasks, we
use a cross-entropy loss during training.
4.4 Results
In Tables 2 and 3, we report train and test accu-
racy for the text and image datasets respectively.
MNIST2 is omitted for brevity since all models
successfully achieve perfect scores. This validates
our setup and confirms that HAM, PEFF, and SIM
learn correctly. In the SST2 task, HAM performs
competitively with baseline methods using a simi-
lar number of parameters, outperforming simpler
models like LOG, MLP and RNN, and ranking
just below the LSTM and QLSTM. AG News and
IMDb turn out to be easier tasks, with SIM achiev-
ing scores comparable to the baselines and accu-
racy being high for all models. CIFAR2 proves
to be a hard task, likely due to the images be-
ing coloured rather than grayscale and having a
higher resolution: while HAM and PEFF score
relatively higher than the LOG baseline, SIM un-
derperforms, possibly due to its relatively simple
decision boundary. We speculate that a higher num-
ber of Pauli strings would narrow this gap, as more
complex transformations would increase the capac-
ity of the model. On Fashion, SIM performs better
than LOG but worse than other baselines. Notably,
CIRC achieves relatively high performance. Across
tasks, PEFF and SIM attain performance compa-
rable with the baseline despite the low parameter
count. PEFF confirms our intuition that simply
7
CIFAR2 Fashion
Model Params Train Test Params Train Test
LOG 1025 73.9 72.9 1025 85.5 83.5
MLP 112701 89.0 83.4 89610 87.9 85.8
CNN 75329 96.3 94.1 130250 95.4 90.7
CIRC 2081 85.1 84.6 11094 89.2 86.5
QCNN 169 84.9 84.7 558 76.7 76.3
HAM 523818 89.6 81.0 - - -
PEFF 1056 79.3 78.7 - - -
SIM 2156 68.9 68.2 10934 87.6 84.4
Table 3: Accuracies across image datasets. Results are
averaged over 10 runs.
# Params Train Test*
HAM 130854 91.2 82.3
PEFF 410 81.8 80.0
SIM 9410 84.5 80.1
STATEIN 130854 92.0 80.2
NOBIAS 38 70.0 71.9
Table 4: Accuracies of additional variants on SST2.
Results are averaged over 10 runs or (*) run achieving
best train accuracy.
skewing points in the embedding space can substi-
tute the bulky bias term over the whole Hamilto-
nian, while SIM confirms that performance can be
retained even with a Hamiltonian composed of few
Pauli strings. The high parameter count of HAM
in MNIST2 and CIFAR2 is necessary to encode
full-size images, resulting in large Hamiltonians.
Across quantum models, we find no clear link be-
tween entangling circuits and performance; non-
entangling baselines often perform best, aligning
with prior findings (Bowles et al., 2024).
We perform additional experiments in Appendix
C and find evidence that the number of Pauli strings
is strongly linked with better performance. Specifi-
cally, larger models with more Pauli strings exhibit
higher accuracy and more stable training dynamics
(Figure 3). Notably, between 500 and 1000 Pauli
strings are already sufficient to match the perfor-
mance of classical baselines on most tasks. This
result aligns with our expectations, as increasing
the number of Pauli strings enables the model to
capture more complex features, as demonstrated in
Eq. 9. Furthermore, we find that removing the bias
term significantly worsens performance, underlin-
ing the importance of this component.
2 4 6 8 10
Epoch
0.60
0.65
0.70
0.75
0.80
0.85
0.90T est accuracy
AG News test accuracy
# Pauli strings
50
100
500
1000
2 4 6 8 10
Epoch
0.55
0.60
0.65
0.70
0.75
0.80
0.85T est accuracy
Fashion test accuracy
# Pauli strings
50
100
500
1000
Figure 3: Performance on the test sets for different
number of Pauli strings in the SIM model. First 10
epochs out of 30 shown.
5 Discussion and future work
This work extends the scalability of flipped models
and makes it possible to process significantly larger
inputs. Moreover, it demonstrates their importance
as a viable quantum method for NLP tasks. The
proposed HAM design encodes input data directly
as a measurement, obtaining performance compara-
ble with other specialized models. The PEFF vari-
ant reduces its parameter complexity, and the SIM
variant additionally reduces its sample complex-
ity, offering a scheme that may be more efficiently
implemented on quantum hardware. Notably, our
method already scales well enough to allow mean-
ingful studies on large datasets using simulators.
The Hamiltonian classifier is presently a proof of
concept meant to illustrate a novel input scheme for
quantum devices with the ultimate goal of expand-
ing the tools available to QML researchers. Future
works could characterize the effectiveness of our
approach on even larger problems and its integra-
tion with existing classical pipelines. Other studies
could consider local strings in conjunction with
8
classical shadows techniques to lower sample com-
plexity. A way of learning more complex functions
could be to stack several layers of Hamiltonian
encoding, possibly performing nonlinear transfor-
mations. On the same thread, our Hamiltonian clas-
sifier could be reformulated as a feature extractor,
allowing in to be integrated into hybrid quantum-
classical pipelines. Other directions deserving a
paper of their own are noise simulation and physi-
cal implementations on real quantum hardware.
Limitations
This work does not evaluate HAM and PEFF in
multi-class scenarios. Although a one-vs-many
approach similar to SIM could be applied, simu-
lating a separate Hamiltonian for each class would
demand substantial computational resources. In-
stead, we prioritized comprehensive hyperparame-
ter search and experimentation on a wider selection
of datasets to provide a better assessment of these
methods’ performance.
We are limited to a small number of qubits and
Pauli strings due to constraints in our implemen-
tation of the Hamiltonians. While increasing the
qubit count of our system could enhance perfor-
mance, a key strength of our approach is that it
does not require a large number of qubits to op-
erate effectively at scales already meaningful for
NLP tasks.
Although our results do not yet match state-of-
the-art NLP models, this work highlights the po-
tential of large-scale quantum architectures, mark-
ing an important step toward practical applications.
Theoretical findings on flipped models suggest that
realizing a definitive advantage will require more
advanced quantum devices than those presently
available (Jerbi et al., 2024), making it unrealistic
to expect these models to surpass classical coun-
terparts at this stage. Consistent with prior efforts
such as Xu et al. (2024), our emphasis remains
on scalability rather than immediate performance
parity with classical methods.
Noisy simulations and real hardware implemen-
tation fall outside the scope of this work, as the cur-
rent model was not designed with noise resilience
in mind.
References
Amira Abbas, David Sutter, Christa Zoufal, Aurelien
Lucchi, Alessio Figalli, and Stefan Woerner. 2021.
The power of quantum neural networks. Nature Com-
putational Science, 1(6).
Eric R Anschuetz and Bobak T Kiani. 2022. Quan-
tum variational algorithms are swamped with traps.
Nature Communications, 13(1):7760.
Sahel Ashhab. 2022. Quantum state preparation proto-
col for encoding classical data into the amplitudes
of a quantum information processing register’s wave
function. Phys. Rev. Res., 4:013091.
Johannes Bausch. 2020. Recurrent quantum neural net-
works. In Advances in Neural Information Process-
ing Systems 33: Annual Conference on Neural In-
formation Processing Systems 2020, NeurIPS 2020,
December 6-12, 2020, virtual.
Yoshua Bengio, Réjean Ducharme, and Pascal Vincent.
2000. A neural probabilistic language model. In Ad-
vances in Neural Information Processing Systems 13,
Papers from Neural Information Processing Systems
(NIPS) 2000, Denver, CO, USA, pages 932–938. MIT
Press.
Jacob Biamonte, Peter Wittek, Nicola Pancotti,
Patrick Rebentrost, Nathan Wiebe, and Seth Lloyd.
2017. Quantum machine learning. Nature,
549(7671):195–202.
Joseph Bowles, Shahnawaz Ahmed, and Maria Schuld.
2024. Better than classical? the subtle art of
benchmarking quantum machine learning models.
Preprint, arXiv:2403.07059.
Daan Camps, Roel Van Beeumen, and Chao Yang. 2021.
Quantum fourier transform revisited. Numerical Lin-
ear Algebra with Applications, 28(1):e2331.
Matthias C. Caro, Hsin-Yuan Huang, M. Cerezo, Kunal
Sharma, Andrew Sornborger, Lukasz Cincio, and
Patrick J. Coles. 2022. Generalization in quantum
machine learning from few training data. Nature
Communications, 13(1):4919.
M. Cerezo, Andrew Arrasmith, Ryan Babbush, Simon C.
Benjamin, Suguru Endo, Keisuke Fujii, Jarrod R. Mc-
Clean, Kosuke Mitarai, Xiao Yuan, Lukasz Cincio,
and Patrick J. Coles. 2021. Variational quantum al-
gorithms. Nature Reviews Physics, 3(9).
Avimita Chatterjee, Koustubh Phalak, and Swaroop
Ghosh. 2023. Quantum error correction for dummies.
In Proceedings - 2023 IEEE International Confer-
ence on Quantum Computing and Engineering, QCE
2023, Proceedings - 2023 IEEE International Confer-
ence on Quantum Computing and Engineering, QCE
2023, pages 70–81, United States. Institute of Elec-
trical and Electronics Engineers Inc. Publisher Copy-
right: © 2023 IEEE.; 4th IEEE International Con-
ference on Quantum Computing and Engineering,
QCE 2023 ; Conference date: 17-09-2023 Through
22-09-2023.
9
Samuel Yen-Chi Chen, Chih-Min Huang, Chia-Wei Hs-
ing, and Ying-Jer Kao. 2021. An end-to-end trainable
hybrid classical-quantum classifier. Machine Learn-
ing: Science and Technology, 2(4):045021.
Samuel Yen-Chi Chen, Shinjae Yoo, and Yao-Lung L.
Fang. 2022. Quantum long short-term memory. In
ICASSP 2022 - 2022 IEEE International Confer-
ence on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing
(ICASSP), pages 8622–8626.
Yixiong Chen. 2022. Quantum dilated convolutional
neural networks. IEEE Access, 10:20240–20246.
El Amine Cherrat, Iordanis Kerenidis, Natansh Mathur,
Jonas Landman, Martin Strahm, and Yun Yvonna
Li. 2022. Quantum vision transformers. Preprint,
arXiv:2209.08167.
Iris Cong, Soonwon Choi, and Mikhail D. Lukin. 2019.
Quantum convolutional neural networks. Nature
Physics, 15(12).
Pierre-Luc Dallaire-Demers and Nathan Killoran. 2018.
Quantum generative adversarial networks. Phys. Rev.
A, 98:012324.
Yuxuan Du, Min-Hsiu Hsieh, Tongliang Liu, and
Dacheng Tao. 2020. Expressive power of
parametrized quantum circuits. Phys. Rev. Res. ,
2:033125.
Edward Farhi and Hartmut Neven. 2018. Classification
with quantum neural networks on near term proces-
sors. arXiv: Quantum Physics.
Lov K. Grover. 1996. A fast quantum mechanical al-
gorithm for database search. In Proceedings of the
Twenty-Eighth Annual ACM Symposium on Theory
of Computing, STOC ’96, page 212–219, New York,
NY , USA. Association for Computing Machinery.
Casper Gyurik and Vedran Dunjko. 2022. On estab-
lishing learning separations between classical and
quantum machine learning with classical data. arXiv
preprint arXiv:2208.06339.
Lukas Hantzko, Lennart Binkowski, and Sabhyata
Gupta. 2024. Tensorized pauli decomposition al-
gorithm. Physica Scripta, 99(8):085128.
Aram W. Harrow, Avinatan Hassidim, and Seth Lloyd.
2009. Quantum algorithm for linear systems of equa-
tions. Phys. Rev. Lett., 103:150502.
Maxwell Henderson, Samriddhi Shakya, Shashindra
Pradhan, and Tristan Cook. 2020. Quanvolutional
neural networks: powering image recognition with
quantum circuits. Quantum Machine Intelligence ,
2(1):2.
Hsin-Yuan Huang, Richard Kueng, and John Preskill.
2020. Predicting many properties of a quantum sys-
tem from very few measurements. Nature Physics,
16(10):1050–1057.
Po-Wei Huang and Patrick Rebentrost. 2024. Post-
variational quantum neural networks. Preprint,
arXiv:2307.10560.
Sofiene Jerbi, Casper Gyurik, Simon C. Marshall, Ric-
cardo Molteni, and Vedran Dunjko. 2024. Shadows
of quantum machine learning. Nature Communica-
tions, 15(1):5676.
Nathan Killoran, Thomas R. Bromley, Juan Miguel Ar-
razola, Maria Schuld, Nicolás Quesada, and Seth
Lloyd. 2019. Continuous-variable quantum neural
networks. Physical Review Research, 1(3).
Océane Koska, Marc Baboulin, and Arnaud Gazda.
2024. A tree-approach pauli decomposition algo-
rithm with application to quantum computing. In ISC
High Performance 2024 Research Paper Proceedings
(39th International Conference), pages 1–11.
Alex Krizhevsky. 2012. Learning multiple layers of
features from tiny images. University of Toronto.
Martin Larocca, Supanut Thanasilp, Samson Wang,
Kunal Sharma, Jacob Biamonte, Patrick J Coles,
Lukasz Cincio, Jarrod R McClean, Zoë Holmes,
and M Cerezo. 2024. A review of barren plateaus
in variational quantum computing. arXiv preprint
arXiv:2405.00781.
Yanan Li, Zhimin Wang, Rongbing Han, Shangshang
Shi, Jiaxin Li, Ruimin Shang, Haiyong Zheng, Guo-
qiang Zhong, and Yongjian Gu. 2023. Quantum re-
current neural networks for sequential learning. Neu-
ral Networks, 166:148–161.
Junhua Liu, Kwan Hui Lim, Kristin L Wood, Wei
Huang, Chu Guo, and He-Liang Huang. 2021. Hy-
brid quantum-classical convolutional neural net-
works. Science China Physics, Mechanics & As-
tronomy, 64(9):290311.
Robin Lorenz, Anna Pearson, Konstantinos Meichanet-
zidis, Dimitri Kartsaklis, and Bob Coecke. 2021.
Qnlp in practice: Running compositional models
of meaning on a quantum computer, doi: 10.48550.
arXiv preprint arXiv.2102.12846.
Andrew L. Maas, Raymond E. Daly, Peter T. Pham,
Dan Huang, Andrew Y . Ng, and Christopher Potts.
2011. Learning word vectors for sentiment analysis.
In Proceedings of the 49th Annual Meeting of the
Association for Computational Linguistics: Human
Language Technologies, pages 142–150, Portland,
Oregon, USA. Association for Computational Lin-
guistics.
Chris Mingard, Jessica Pointing, Charles London, Yoon-
soo Nam, and Ard A. Louis. 2024. Exploiting the
equivalence between quantum neural networks and
perceptrons. Preprint, arXiv:2407.04371.
K. Mitarai, M. Negoro, M. Kitagawa, and K. Fujii. 2018.
Quantum circuit learning. Phys. Rev. A, 98:032309.
10
Michael A. Nielsen and Isaac L. Chuang. 2000. Quan-
tum Computation and Quantum Information. Cam-
bridge University Press.
John Preskill. 2018. Quantum Computing in the NISQ
era and beyond. Quantum, 2:79.
Adrián Pérez-Salinas, Alba Cervera-Lierta, Elies Gil-
Fuster, and José I. Latorre. 2020. Data re-uploading
for a universal quantum classifier. Quantum, 4:226.
Nils Quetschlich, Mathias Soeken, Prakash Murali, and
Robert Wille. 2024. Utilizing resource estimation for
the development of quantum computing applications.
Preprint, arXiv:2402.12434.
Minati Rath and Hema Date. 2023. Quantum data
encoding: A comparative analysis of classical-
to-quantum mapping techniques and their im-
pact on machine learning accuracy. Preprint,
arXiv:2311.10375.
Jonathan Romero, Jonathan P Olson, and Alan Aspuru-
Guzik. 2017. Quantum autoencoders for efficient
compression of quantum data. Quantum Science and
Technology, 2(4).
M. Schuld and F. Petruccione. 2021. Machine Learning
with Quantum Computers . Quantum Science and
Technology. Springer International Publishing.
Maria Schuld, Alex Bocharov, Krysta M. Svore, and
Nathan Wiebe. 2020. Circuit-centric quantum classi-
fiers. Phys. Rev. A, 101:032308.
Maria Schuld and Nathan Killoran. 2022. Is quantum
advantage the right goal for quantum machine learn-
ing? PRX Quantum, 3:030101.
Arsenii Senokosov, Alexandr Sedykh, Asel Sagin-
galieva, Basil Kyriacou, and Alexey Melnikov. 2024.
Quantum machine learning for image classifica-
tion. Machine Learning: Science and Technology ,
5(1):015040.
Jinjing Shi, Ren-Xin Zhao, Wenxuan Wang, Shichao
Zhang, and Xuelong Li. 2023. Qsan: A near-term
achievable quantum self-attention network. Preprint,
arXiv:2207.07563.
Peter W. Shor. 1997. Polynomial-time algorithms for
prime factorization and discrete logarithms on a quan-
tum computer. SIAM Journal on Computing, 26(5).
Sukin Sim, Peter D. Johnson, and Alán Aspuru-Guzik.
2019. Expressibility and entangling capability of
parameterized quantum circuits for hybrid quantum-
classical algorithms. Advanced Quantum Technolo-
gies, 2(12).
Richard Socher, Alex Perelygin, Jean Wu, Jason
Chuang, Christopher D. Manning, Andrew Ng, and
Christopher Potts. 2013. Recursive deep models for
semantic compositionality over a sentiment treebank.
In Proc. of EMNLP, pages 1631–1642, Seattle, Wash-
ington, USA. Association for Computational Linguis-
tics.
Yanqi Song, Yusen Wu, Shengyao Wu, Dandan Li,
Qiaoyan Wen, Sujuan Qin, and Fei Gao. 2023. A
quantum federated learning framework for classical
clients. Preprint, arXiv:2312.11672.
Yigit Subasi, Zoe Holmes, Nolan Coble, and Andrew
Sornborger. 2023. On nonlinear transformations in
quantum computation. In APS March Meeting Ab-
stracts, volume 2023 of APS Meeting Abstracts, page
M64.009.
Alex Wang, Amanpreet Singh, Julian Michael, Felix
Hill, Omer Levy, and Samuel R. Bowman. 2019.
GLUE: A multi-task benchmark and analysis plat-
form for natural language understanding. In Proc. of
ICLR. OpenReview.net.
Hefeng Wang, S. Ashhab, and Franco Nori. 2009. Ef-
ficient quantum algorithm for preparing molecular-
system-like states on a quantum computer. Physical
Review A, 79(4).
ShiJie Wei, YanHu Chen, ZengRong Zhou, and GuiLu
Long. 2022. A quantum convolutional neural net-
work on nisq devices. AAPPS Bulletin, 32(1):2.
Marco Wiedmann, Marc Hölle, Maniraman Periyasamy,
Nico Meyer, Christian Ufrecht, Daniel D Scherer,
Axel Plinge, and Christopher Mutschler. 2023. An
empirical comparison of optimizers for quantum ma-
chine learning with spsa-based gradients. In 2023
IEEE International Conference on Quantum Comput-
ing and Engineering (QCE), volume 1, pages 450–
456. IEEE.
David Wierichs, Josh Izaac, Cody Wang, and Cedric
Yen-Yu Lin. 2022. General parameter-shift rules for
quantum gradients. Quantum, 6:677.
Sixuan Wu, Jian Li, Peng Zhang, and Yue Zhang. 2021.
Natural language processing meets quantum physics:
A survey and categorization. In Proceedings of the
2021 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural
Language Processing, pages 3172–3182, Online and
Punta Cana, Dominican Republic. Association for
Computational Linguistics.
Han Xiao, Kashif Rasul, and Roland V ollgraf. 2017.
Fashion-mnist: a novel image dataset for bench-
marking machine learning algorithms. Preprint,
arXiv:1708.07747.
Wenduan Xu, Stephen Clark, Douglas Brown, Gabriel
Matos, and Konstantinos Meichanetzidis. 2024.
Quantum recurrent architectures for text classifica-
tion. In Proceedings of the 2024 Conference on Em-
pirical Methods in Natural Language Processing ,
pages 18020–18027, Miami, Florida, USA. Associa-
tion for Computational Linguistics.
Zebo Yang, Maede Zolanvari, and Raj Jain. 2023. A
survey of important issues in quantum computing and
communications. IEEE Communications Surveys &
Tutorials, 25(2):1059–1094.
11
Kamila Zaman, Alberto Marchisio, Muhammad Abdul-
lah Hanif, and Muhammad Shafique. 2023. A survey
on quantum machine learning: Current trends, chal-
lenges, opportunities, and the road ahead. Preprint,
arXiv:2310.10315.
Xiang Zhang, Junbo Zhao, and Yann LeCun. 2015.
Character-level convolutional networks for text clas-
sification. In Advances in Neural Information Pro-
cessing Systems, volume 28. Curran Associates, Inc.
Ren-Xin Zhao, Jinjing Shi, and Xuelong Li. 2024. Qk-
san: A quantum kernel self-attention network. IEEE
Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intel-
ligence, pages 1–12.
A Quantum computing fundamentals
Quantum computers are conceptually and physi-
cally different devices from classical computers.
Instead of basing their logic on binary data repre-
sentations implemented by transistors, they utilize
the rules of quantum physics as a substrate for com-
putation. For this reason, in what follows we de-
scribe the building blocks of quantum computation.
Dirac notation Quantum computing makes ex-
tensive use of Dirac notation (also called bra-ket
notation) to simplify the representation of linear
transformations which are commonplace in the the-
ory. The fundamental elements of this notation are
bras and kets. A ket, denoted as |ψ⟩, represents a
column vector ψ in a Hilbert space. A bra, denoted
as ⟨ϕ|, represents instead a vector in the dual space
(the complex conjugate transpose of a ket). The in-
ner product of two vectorsϕ and ψ, which results in
a scalar, is written as ⟨ϕ⟩ψ. Conversely, the outer
product |ψ⟩⟨ϕ|, forms a matrix or an operator.
Quantum systems The basic unit of informa-
tion in a quantum computer is a two-dimensional
quantum bit (qubit) which is mathematically mod-
elled by a normalized column vector, the state vec-
tor, in a two-dimensional vector space equipped
with an inner-product, or Hilbert space. A state
vector is usually expressed concisely in Dirac no-
tation as |ψ⟩ =

α β
⊤ ∈ C2. We say that a
qubit |ψ⟩ := α |0⟩ + β |1⟩ is in a coherent quan-
tum superposition of two orthonormal basis states
|0⟩ :=

1 0
⊤ and |1⟩ :=

0 1
⊤, such that the
complex coefficients in the basis expansion satisfy
normalization constraint |α|2 + |β|2 = 1. This
constraint originates from physics: in order to ex-
tract any information from a quantum state, we
need to measure it in a chosen basis, which de-
stroys the superposition in the measured basis by
projecting the state |ψ⟩ on one of the basis ele-
ments. If we measure state |ψ⟩ in the {|0⟩, |1⟩}
basis, we get outcome " 0" with probability |α|2
and the post-measurement state becomes |0⟩, and
respectively, we get "1" with probability |β|2 and
post-measurement state |1⟩.
Multi-qubit systems In order to model a quan-
tum system with multiple qubits, we use the so-
called Kronecker product (⊗) to combine many
individual state vectors into a single larger one. An
n-qubit system can be represented by a vector of
size N = 2n, |ψ1 . . . ψn⟩ := |ψ1⟩⊗···⊗| ψn⟩. In a
chosen basis, the entries of this vector describe the
probability of observing that outcome. Many QML
approaches aim to gain a quantum advantage by
manipulating only a few qubits to access an expo-
nentially large Hilbert space. To give an example,
if two qubits |ψ1⟩ and |ψ2⟩ are both initialized in
(|0⟩ + |1⟩)/
√
2, the joint state is given by an equal
superposition of all the possible n = 2bit string
vectors
|ψ1⟩ ⊗ |ψ2⟩ = |00⟩ + |01⟩ + |10⟩ + |11⟩
2 .
In this setup, measurement can performed sepa-
rately on each qubit, resulting in a n-element bit-
string.
Quantum circuits Quantum computation is
achieved by manipulating qubits. This is done
using quantum gates. Any n-qubit gate can be
represented as a unitary matrix U ∈ CN×N which
acts on the n-qubit input state |ψ⟩ via the usual
matrix-vector multiplication, giving output U |ψ⟩.
Intuitively, quantum gates can be considered as ro-
tations that conserve the length of a state vector. A
sequence of gates applied on one or many qubits
is called a quantum circuit. By construction, uni-
tary circuits perform linear operations. Non-linear
computation requires workarounds like running the
computation on a larger Hilbert space and measur-
ing output qubits in a subspace or re-uploading in-
put data (Killoran et al., 2019; Pérez-Salinas et al.,
2020; Subasi et al., 2023).
Pauli decomposition A concise way of express-
ing multiple measurements on multiple qubits over
multiple bases is through a so-called Hamiltonian.
A Hamiltonian H for an n-qubit system is a Her-
mitian matrix of size 2n × 2n. The result of a
measurement of a state ψ with a specific Hamil-
tonian H can be expressed as ⟨ψ|H |ψ⟩, which is
the expectation value of this measurement. The
2 × 2 Pauli matrices, P = {X, Y, Z, I}, or more
generally multi-body Pauli operators, also called
Pauli strings, Pn = {Nn
i=1 Oi|Oi ∈ P}form a
12
basis for Hermitian matrices of dimension 2n × 2n.
Consequently, any Hamiltonian can be expressed
as a linear combination of Pauli strings:
H =
X
i
αiPi where αi ∈ R and Pi ∈ Pn.
This decomposition results in O(4n) unique Pauli
strings, each representing a physical property that
can be measured using quantum devices. Generic
Hamiltonians are expensive to decompose and mea-
sure due to the exponential number of Pauli strings.
For this reason, in VQC settings, typical Hamilto-
nians are constructed from a polynomial number
of Pauli strings.
B Hyperparameter tuning
For each architecture and for each dataset in our
evaluation, we perform a randomised search for the
best parameters: we randomly select 50 configu-
rations, train them on the task and evaluate their
performance on the development set. To avoid over-
fitting, we perform early stopping on the training if
development loss does not decrease for five consec-
utive epochs. Troughout all experiments, we utilize
the Adam optimizer provided by PyTorch. Since
our largest model HAM has at most∼ 500k param-
eters (dictated by the embedding space), we limit
the random search to configuration with less-than
or equal number of parameters to ensure a fair com-
parison. In practice, we find RNNs, LSTMs and
CNNs perform very well with as low as40k param-
eters. What follows is a list of all hyperparameters
we evaluated:
• Batch size: [64, 128, 256];
• Learning rate: [10−2, 10−3, 10−4];
• Hidden size: For RNNs and LSTMs, the size
of the hidden representation [100, 300, 500];
• Layers: For RNNs and LSTMs, the number
of layers of the recurrent block [1, 4, 8]. For
MLP, the total number of layers including in-
put and output [3, 4, 5]. For CNNs, the total
number of convolutional layers [3, 4, 5]. For
HAM, PEFF, SIM and CIRC, the number of
repeated applications of the ansatz, analogous
to the number of layers [8, 16, 32];
• Channels: For CNNs, the number of out-
put channels of each convolutional layer
[8, 16, 32, 64, 128];
RX RY RZ
RX RY RZ
RX RY RZ
(a)
RY RX RY RX
RY RX RY RX
RY RX RY RX
(b)
RX RZ RX RX RX RZ
RX RZ RX RX RX RZ
RX RZ RX RX RX RZ
(c)
Figure 4: Circuit ansätze explored in the experiment.
For the sake of visualization, the image shows ansätze
for n = 3. Since the experiments use different values,
we extend the patterns to act on more qubits. (a) Non-
entangling ansatz (b) Ring ansatz (c) All-to-all ansatz.
(b) and (c) are respectively circuit 14 and 6 from (Sim
et al., 2019)
• Kernel size: For CNNs, the kernel dimension
of each convolutional layer [3, 5, 7];
• Circuit: The ansatz Uθ used to prepare state
ψ. We experiment with three hardware-
efficient ansätze inspired by circuits from Sim
et al. (2019) and illustrated in Figure 4. These
ansätze are designed to explore different lev-
els of entanglement (the quantum counter-
part of correlation) and gate complexity. The
first is a non-entangling circuit composed of
single-qubit rotations, exhibiting linear com-
plexity with respect to the number of qubits.
The second is an entangling circuit arranged
in a ring configuration, also scaling linearly
in gate count. The third is an all-to-all en-
tangling circuit, which scales quadratically.
[Baseline, Ring, All-to-all].
• # Pauli strings: For SIM, the number of
Pauli strings composing the Hamiltonian
[50, 100, 500, 1000].
Tables 5 and 6 shows the final selection of best-
performing hyperparameters used in the main ex-
periment of Section 4.3.
C Supplementary Experiments
C.1 Removing bias hurts performance
To further evaluate our models and assess the im-
pact of key design choices, we conduct an ablation
study using the SST2 dataset. As in the main ex-
periment, we begin with the optimal set of hyperpa-
13
LOG
Dataset Batch size Learning rate
SST2 64 10−3
IMDb 64 10−2
AG News 64 10−2
MNIST2 128 10−3
CIFAR2 256 10−3
Fashion 64 10−3
MLP
Dataset Batch size Learning rate Hidden size Layers
SST2 64 10−4 300 3
IMDb 64 10−3 300 3
AG News 64 10−3 100 3
MNIST2 256 10−4 100 3
CIFAR2 128 10−4 100 3
Fashion 256 10−3 100 3
LSTM
Dataset Batch size Learning rate Hidden size Layers
SST2 64 10−2 100 2
IMDb 128 10−2 100 2
AG News 128 10−3 100 2
RNN
Dataset Batch size Learning rate Hidden size Layers
SST2 64 10−4 100 1
IMDb 256 10−4 100 2
AG News 256 10−4 100 1
CNN
Dataset Batch size Learning rate Layers Channels Kernel Size
MNIST2 64 10−3 5 16 5
CIFAR2 64 10−4 4 32 5
Fashion 64 10−3 4 16 3
CIRC
Dataset Batch size Learning rate Circuit Layers
SST2 256 10−3 All-to-all 8
AG News 128 10−3 Baseline 16
IMDb 128 10−3 All-to-all 16
MNIST2 128 10−3 Baseline 8
CIFAR2 64 10−3 Baseline 8
Fashion 256 10−3 Ring 32
Table 5: Best hyperparameters across all baseline models and tasks
14
HAM
Dataset Batch size Learning rate Circuit Layers
SST2 128 10−3 Ring 8
IMDb 256 10−3 All-to-all 32
MNIST2 256 10−2 Baseline 32
CIFAR2 64 10−3 Ring 8
PEFF
Dataset Batch size Learning rate Circuit Layers
SST2 64 10−2 All-to-all 8
IMDb 64 10−2 All-to-all 8
MNIST2 64 10−3 All-to-all 8
CIFAR2 256 10−2 Baseline 16
SIM
Dataset Batch size Learning rate Circuit Layers # Pauli strings
SST2 256 10−3 Ring 32 1000
IMDb 256 10−2 All-to-all 16 1000
AG News 128 10−3 All-to-all 16 1000
MNIST2 256 10−2 Ring 32 1000
CIFAR2 64 10−3 All-to-all 32 1000
Fashion 256 10−2 All-to-all 8 1000
Table 6: Best hyperparameters across all Hamiltonian models and tasks
rameters identified in Appendix B, apply changes
to the architecture, and run 10 separate runs. Fi-
nally, we report the test set performance of the run
achieving the lowest loss as reported on the GLUE
website.
In this ablation study, we examine the role of
the bias term in contributing to downstream perfor-
mance. Our best-performing model, HAM, delivers
strong results but does so with a large number of
parameters. In contrast, PEFF offers slightly lower
performance but significantly reduces the parame-
ter count, as detailed in Section 4.4. To explore the
impact of the bias term we completely remove it
and assess the performance of the resulting model,
referring to this variant as NOBIAS:
Hϕ(x) := 1
s
sX
i=1
xix⊤
i . (10)
The results, summarized in Table 4, show a marked
decrease in performance. The 71.9% accuracy
achieved by NOBIAS is nonetheless surprising
given the model is stripped of almost all param-
eters. We hypothesize that, in HAM, the bias term
influences the eigenvalues of the Hamiltonian, di-
rectly affecting the final expectation value. For
PEFF, the bias appears to shift the embeddings into
a region more favourable for classification. We fur-
ther speculate that NOBIAS could achieve results
similar to PEFF by simply unfreezing the input em-
beddings during training; this would allow them to
shift as in the other variants.
C.2 Additional state preparation leads to
overfitting
In this section we investigate whether combining
our HAM architecture with a standard state prepa-
ration routine improves model performance. Also,
in this experiment, we consider SST2, with the
configuration of the main text unchanged but for
the additional state preparation. We call this setup
STATEIN (short for STATE INput):
˜x := 1
s
sX
i=1
˜xi (11)
ψθ := Uθ |˜x⟩ (12)
In this configuration, Uθ acts not on the zero-state,
but on an initial state |˜x⟩ in which the input data
has been amplitude-encoded. We hypothesize that
applying Uθ directly to the encoded inputs might
enable the model to better identify useful features
15
2 4 6 8 10
Epoch
0.5
0.6
0.7
0.8
0.9Train accuracy
AG News train accuracy
# Pauli strings
50
100
500
1000
2 4 6 8 10
Epoch
0.5
0.6
0.7
0.8Train accuracy
Fashion train accuracy
# Pauli strings
50
100
500
1000
Figure 5: Performance on the train set for different
number of Pauli strings in the SIM model. Error bars
are shown for all choices but grow thin for the two
largest models. First 10 epochs out of 30 shown.
for classification. Results displayed in Table 4
show a slight improvement in training accuracy,
with STATEIN achieving an average of 92.0% over
10 runs compared to 91.1% for HAM. However,
the test accuracy only marginally exceeds that of
PEFF and is noticeably lower than HAM, suggest-
ing that the combination of Hamiltonian encoding
and amplitude-encoded inputs may lead to overfit-
ting. While these results provide some insights, a
more thorough analysis of the interaction between
state preparation and input-encoded measurement
is needed, which we leave for future research.
C.3 The number of Pauli strings correlates
with performance
Rewriting the SIM model leads to a bilinear form
where each Pauli string acts as a transformation on
the input (Eq. 9). During hyperparameter tuning,
we consistently observe that the best-performing
SIM models use 1000 Pauli strings across all ex-
periments. We hypothesize that this is due to the
distinct transformation each Pauli string introduces,
which enriches the model’s feature set. This raises
some questions: does increasing the number of
Pauli strings, and thus the number of transforma-
tions, lead to better performance? Moreover, how
does the generalization capability scale with the
number of Pauli strings?
To explore this, we use the same configurations
found for the AG News and Fashion datasets but
vary the number of Pauli strings. Results are dis-
played in Figures 3 and 5. Low string count do
not perform much better than chance, but accu-
racy steadily increases and eventually plateaus at
1000 strings, reaching levels comparable to other
models like MLP and CIRC. Increasing the num-
ber of strings also leads to a more stable training
process as highlighted by the error bars growing
thin for p = 500and 1000. This suggests the loss
landscape may become smoother as more transfor-
mations are added, facilitating training. This is a
promising outcome: it suggests that transforma-
tions induced by Pauli strings actively contribute to
learning by creating more complex features. It also
indicates that a relatively small number of strings
can effectively substitute for a full decomposition.
We speculate that increasing the number of Pauli
strings beyond 1000 could significantly improve
results for more complex datasets like CIFAR2,
where performance currently lags.
16

